Guide to the Karl Menger Papers, 1872-2000 RL.00888
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Writings and Research Series, 1921-1983 and undated; 2
  - Essays and Articles, 2
    - Intuitionismus und Formalismus, undated (Box 17)
      Handwritten
    - Is ∫cos x dx = ∫ cos y dy? Yes and No, undated (Box 17)
    - Mathematical Study of Underground Movements, undated (Box 17)
      With H. Ian Whitlock, Preliminary Report; incl. draft
    - Memories of Beatrice Pearson de Lany, undated (Box 17)
    - My Memories of the Early Days of I.I.T., undated (Box 17)
    - On Probably Optimal Differences in Differential Calculus, undated (Box 17)
    - On the Pictorial Representation of Sets of Physical Objects, undated (Box 17)
    - Outline of a Theory of Ortho-Planes, undated (Box 17)
    - Postulational Method, undated (Box 17)
    - Raising Funds for Common Enterprises, undated (Box 18)
    - Razor and Separator, undated (Box 18)
    - Remarks about the New Foundation of Hyperbolic and Related Geometries, undated (Box 18)
    - Resumé of the Theory of Variables and Fluents, undated (Box 18)
    - Substitutive Function Algebra and the Calculus of Propositions, undated (Box 18)
      Includes copies with comments and draft
    - The Application of Analysis to Physical Science, undated (Box 18)
    - The Derivative of a Function, undated (Box 18)
    - The Geometry of the Man in the Street, undated (Box 18)
    - The Raising of Funds for Joint Purposes, undated (Box 18)
    - The Semantics of Mathematical Analysis and Its Application to Science, undated (Box 18)
    - Über die Gedankenrichtung und die Haupttendenzen des Wiener mathematischen Kolloquiums (Box 18)
    - Über die Nulldimensionalen Mengen, undated (Box 18)
    - Über die Stetigen Bilder der Strecke, undated (Box 18)
    - Untitled (On Differential Equations and Their Teaching), undated (probably 1974) (Box 18)
    - Untitled (On Social Groups), undated (Box 18)
    - Untitled (On Theories), undated (Box 18)
      In German; includes handwritten draft
    - Untitled (1. Eine Extentionale Wertlehre, 2. Exakte Aussagen über Menschengruppen, 3. Quantitative Aussagen über Willensgruppen), undated (probably 1934-1936) (Box 18)
    - Untitled, incomplete works by Menger, undated (Box 18)
      Includes two articles
    - What Does Democracy Mean?, undated (Box 18)
    - Витгенщайн за Формулите и променливите, undated (Box 18)
  - Speeches, 3
    - The Teaching of Intermediate Mathematics, 1958 (Box 18)
      From an Address to the Illinois Section of the Mathematical Association of America
    - What is x?, 1959-1961 (Box 18)
      Summary of Talks before the I.I.T. Mathematics Institute for Secondary School Students of High Ability
    - Remarks on the Algebra of Functors, 1962 (Box 18)
      Conference on Self-Organizing Systems, Museum of Science and Industry, Chicago, Ill.
    - Some Thoughts About the History and the Teaching of Mathematics, 1980 (Box 18)
      Presented at Valparaiso University, Indiana
    - Untitled (About the History and Didactics of Mathematics), undated (Box 18)
    - Untitled (On Modern Mathematics), undated (Box 18)
    - Untitled (Vortrag über Intuitionismus / Presentation on Intuitionism), undated (Box 18)
  - Reviews by Menger, 4
    - Review of: A. Fraenkel; Einleitung in die Mengenlehre, 1929 (Box 18)
    - Review of: E. Kamke; Mengenlehre, 1930 (Box 18)
    - Review of: Edwin A. Abbott; Flächenbrand. Eine Geschichte von den Dimensionen Erzählt von einem Quadrat, 1930 (Box 18)
    - Review of: J. Tinbergen; Minimumsproblemen in de Naturkunde en de Ekonomie, 1930 (Box 18)
    - Review of: Jahrbuch über die Fortschritte der Mathematik, 1932 (Box 18)
    - Review of: Witold Hurewicz and Henry Wallman, Dimension Theory, 1942 (Box 18)
    - Review of: Lucienne Félix; The Modern Aspect of Mathematics, 1962 (Box 18)
    - Review of: Contributions to the Theory of Riemann Surfaces, 1953, undated (Box 18)
  - Reviews of Menger's Works, 5
    - Reviews of: Dimensionstheorie, 1929-1931 (Box 18)
    - Reviews of: Ergebnisse eines Mathematischen Kolloquiums, 1933-1936 (Box 18)
      Reviews of Heft 1, Heft 3 and Heft 6
    - Reviews of: Kurventheorie, 1932-1935 (Box 18)
    - Reviews of: Krise und Neuaufbau in den Exakten Wissenschaften, 1933 (Box 18)
    - Reviews of: Moral, Wille und Weltgestaltung, 1934-1936 (Box 18)
      Includes a list of reviews
    - Reviews of: The New Logic, 1937 (Box 18)
    - Reviews of: You Will Like Geometry, 1952 (Box 18)
    - Reviews of: Calculus. A Modern Approach, 1953-1955 and undated (Box 18)
    - Reviews of: The Basic Concepts of Mathematics. Part I. Algebra, undated (Box 18)
    - Reviews of: Bericht über Metrische Geometrien, 1973 (Box 18)
    - Reviews of: Calculus 1950 - Geometry 1880, 1958 (Box 18)
      Russian
    - Reviews of: Selected Papers in Logic and Foundations, Didactics, Economics, 1980 and undated (Box 18)
  - Miscellaneous, 6
    - Biography of Carl Menger, undated (Box 19)
    - Advertisment for Menger's Publications, 1927-1979 (Box 19)
    - Articles about Menger, 1957-1987 and undated (Box 19)
      Includes newspaper articles, orbituary, reports on presentations
    - Articles Collected by Menger, 1937-1979 and undated (Box 19)
      A variety of newspaper clippings, photocopies, book reviews and articles relevant to Menger and his research.
    - Books edited by Menger, 1941-1942 (Box 19)
      Reports of a Mathematical Colloquium, Second Series, Issue 3 + 4
    - Lists of Menger's Publications, undated (Box 19)
    - Interview mit Professor Dr. Karl Menger, 1978 (Box 19)
      Interview by Werner Schimanovich and Peter Weibel
    - What Mathematics is Really Like, Round Table Discussion on Radio Station WBIK; Karl Menger, Gordon Pall, Haim Reingold, S. S. Shu, L. R. Wilcox, 1952 (Box 19)
    - Scalar Functions of Matrices, Report to Office of Naval Research, Submitted by Deparment of Mathematics, I.I.T., Project Director: Karl Menger, 1953-1954 (Box 19)
      Proposal and final report
    - Funktionsalgebra und Ihre Beziehungen zu Verwandten Theorien, Graz, 15. September 1964 (Box 19)
  - Drafts and Proofs, 7
    - Drafts and proofs, undated; 81 folders (Box 40-44)
      Miscellaneous unsorted and undated drafts and proofs in English and German. Some shorthand used.
    - Drafts and proofs, undated; 11 folders (Box 49)
      Miscellaneous unsorted and undated drafts and proofs.
- Writings by Others, 3
  Arrangement
  Loosely arranged alphabetically.
  - "A", 4 folders (Box 20)
    Including János Aczél, Pawel S. Alexandroff, Nachman Aronszajn, Kenneth J. Arrow
  - "Ba" (Box 20)
  - "Be", 5 folders (Box 20)
    Including Gustav Bergmann, Richard Bellman, Paul A. Benioff, Mary Katherine Bennett
  - "Bl", 2 folders (Box 20)
  - "Bo" (Box 20)
  - "Br", 2 folders (Box 20)
  - "Bu" (Box 20)
  - "Ca" (Box 20)
    Including Rudolf Carnap
  - "Ce" (Box 20)
  - "Ch", 2 folders (Box 20)
    Including Alonzo Church
  - "Cl-Cz", 3 folders (Box 21)
  - "D" (Box 21)
    Including John W. Dawson
  - "E", 4 folders (Box 21)
    Including Hans Eckstein
  - "F", 6 folders (Box 21)
    Including Solomon Feferman, Maurice René Fréchet, Burton D. Fried, Philipp Furtwängler
  - "G", 5 folders (Box 21-22)
    Including Eugene Garfield, Kurt Gödel, Adolf Grünbaum
  - "Ha", 5 folders (Box 22)
    Including Gottfried Haberler, Hans Hahn, Preston C. Hammer, Norwood Russel Hanson, Frank Harary, John C. Harsanyi, Friedrich August von Hayek
  - "He" (Box 22)
  - "Hi" (Box 22)
    Including John Hicks, David Hilbert
  - "Ho" (Box 22)
    Including Gerald Holton, Hans Hornich
  - "Hu", 3 folders (Box 22)
    Including Edward V. Huntington, Witold Hurewicz
  - "I-J" (Box 22)
  - "K", 4 folders (Box 22)
    Including Stuart Kauffman, Mead C. Killion, Stephen C. Kleene, Leopold Kronecker, Harold William Kuhn
  - "L", 6 folders (Box 23)
    Including Donald Charles "Don" Lavoie, Werner Leinfellner, Kenneth O. Leland, Justus von Liebig, Robert Duncan Luce, Günther Ludwig, Wilhelmus Luxemburg
  - "Ma", 2 folders (Box 23)
    Including Ernst Mach
  - "Mc" (Box 23)
    Including Warren S. McCulloch
  - "Me", 3 folders (Box 23)
    Including Hilda Menger, Karl Stephan Menger (Karl S. Menger, Jr.), Fredric M. Menger
  - "Mi" (Box 23)
    Including John Stuart Mill
  - "Mo", 2 folders (Box 23)
    Including Theodor Molien, Oskar Morgenstern
  - "N" (Box 23)
    Including John von Neumann, Allen Newell, Georg Nöbeling
  - "O" (Box 23)
    Including Robert F. O'Connell, Rufus Oldenburger
  - "P", 4 folders (Box 23-24)
    Including Bodo Pareigis, Solomon Passy, Max Planck, Johannes Poinsot (John of St. Thomas), Karl Popper, Hilary Putnam
  - "Q" (Box 24)
    Includes Willard Van Orman Quine
  - "R", 4 folders (Box 24)
    Including Haim Reingold, Marcel Riesz, Kurt W. Rothschild, Erzherzog Rudolf (Kronprinz von Österreich-Ungarn)
  - "Sa" (Box 24)
    Including Eike von Savigny
  - "Sc", 6 folders (Box 24)
    Including Werner Schimanovich, Jürgen Schmidt, Jan A. Schouten, Otto Schreier, Erwin Schrödinger, Berthold Schweizer
  - "Se-Sh", 3 folders (Box 24)
    Including Lloyd S. Shapley, Henry M. Sheffer, Roger N. Shepard
  - "Si" (Box 25)
    Including Carl Ludwig Siegel, Wacław F. Sierpiński, Herbert A. Simon
  - "Sk" (Box 25)
    Including Helen Skala, Abe Sklar
  - "Sm" (Box 25)
  - "So-Sp" (Box 25)
  - "St" (Box 25)
    Including David Ramsay Steele, Stanley Smith Stevens, Erich W. Streissler, Karl Strubecker
  - "Su-Sz" (Box 25)
  - "T", 3 folders (Box 25)
    Including Alfred Tarski, Olga Taussky-Todd, Edward O. Thorp, Gerhard Tintner
  - "U" (Box 25)
    Including Pawel S. Urysohn (Paul Urysohn)
  - "V" (Box 25)
    Including Harry S. Vandiver
  - "W", 6 folders (Box 25)
    Including Friedrich Waismann, Abraham Wald, Hao Wang, Harrison C. White, Gordon Thomas Whyburn, Norbert Wiener, Friedrich von Wieser, Eugene P. Wigner
  - "X" (Box 25)
  - "Z", 2 folders (Box 25)
    Including Shea Zellweger, Heinz Zemanek
  - Unidentified authors, 32 folders (Box 25-26)
- Notebooks and Notes, 4
  This series includes both bound volumes and loose pages of notes, largely kept by Menger (with one subseries of Notebooks by Others). The notebooks' topics are included when known, although Menger appears to have used his notebooks haphazardly and as-needed, resulting in several topics concurrently present in the same notebook.
  - German Notebooks, undated, 8
    - Miscellaneous German notebooks (Box 29, Folder 1)
      Titles and topics include: "Kottler: Theorien der Materie," "Mechanik fester Körper," "Axiomatik des Wünschens," "Galoische Theorie," "Carathéodory: Variationsrechnung in Frank-Mises 2. Auf.," "Generelle Vereinbarkeit," "Distributivgesetz," "Theorie der Einheiten algebraischer Körper"
    - Miscellaneous German notebooks (Box 29, Folder 2)
      Titles and topics include: "Kombin. Topol.," "Hyperkomplexe Zahlen," "Transformationen & ihre Zusammensetzung," "Übertragung der elementaren Zahlentheorie," "Orthogonalsysteme," "Lense," "Lense II," "Zahlenkörper," "Logik, Erkenntnistheorie: ihre Bedeutung für die Philosophie," "Statistische Mechanik," "Plato"
    - Miscellaneous German notebooks,  (Box 29, Folder 3)
      Titles and topics include: "Der Körper K(i)," "regressiv und dominant," "Reidemeister," "Reidemeister II," "Geschid. Math: Transendenz von e & π," "Differentialgeometrie," "Mathem. Probleme," "Hyperkomplexe Zahlen"
    - Miscellaneous German notebooks (Box 29, Folder 4)
      One larger notebook comprised of smaller notebooks and loose notes. Topics and titles include: "Ex. Wissensch.," "Gleichmäßige Aufbringung im Aufbringerkreis," "Spenden und Zwangsabgaben"
    - Miscellaneous German notebooks (Box 46)
      One larger notebook comprised of smaller notebooks and loose notes. Topics and titles include: "Courant Hilbert: Methoden d. mathem. Physik," "Raum," "Vorgelegter Raum," "Positiv fastmetrischer Raum," "Eulersche Gleichung"
    - Looseleaf philosophy notes, removed from at least 2 notebooks (Box 46)
    - Arbeiten aus Studentenzeit: Einfachheitsproblem. (Box 46)
    - "Kolloquiumhefte Rechnungen." Tables of costs with occasional dates (1933-1936). (Box 46)
  - English Notebooks, undated, 9
    - Notebooks, including "A New Introduction to D.E.s with an Appendix" (Box 30, Folder 1)
    - Miscellaneous English notebooks (Box 30, Folder 2)
      Titles and topics include: "Operation Methods," "3 valued 2 place sets," "History new and final for k=3,4 m=2," "n valued 2 place 3 place," "3- & 4-valued," "Tensor Calc," "Tensor," "Theory of Triples," "Complex Functions: A New Approach"
    - Miscellaneous English notebooks (Box 30, Folder 3)
      Titles and topics include: "Wald seq.," "Conchoid of Nicomedes," "Real analysis"
    - Miscellaneous English notebooks (Box 30, Folder 4)
      Titles and topics include: "Sierpinski's idea of weak dimension, etc.," "Topology of domain," "Limits, Theory of Limits"
    - Miscellaneous English notebooks (Box 30, Folder 5)
      Titles and topics include: "Carathéodory Theory," "Operators," "Diff. Eqs"
  - Untitled Notebooks, undated, 10
    - Notebooks in shorthand, 12 folders (Box 31-32)
      Miscellaneous notebooks in German and English shorthand. Untitled and undated.
    - Miscellaneous notes, in English and German (Box 49)
  - Other Notebooks, 11
    - Course Notes, 1920s; 1 folders (Box 33)
      Notebooks filled with Menger's personal notes from courses he took. Some dated, some undated. Titles and topics include: "Zentralprojektion (undated)," "Thirring: Thermodyn. (undated)," "Thirring: Kinetische Gastheorie (undated)," "Furtwängler: Gruppentheorie (1920-21)," "Furtwängler: Theorie der algebraischen Gleichungen (1920-21)," "Furtwängler: Zahlentheorie (1921)," "Furtwängler: Analytische Zahlentheorie (undated)"
    - Lecture Notes, 1930s-?; 1 folders (Box 33)
      Notebooks filled with Menger's notes for courses he taught. Some dated, some undated. Titles and topics include: "Analytische Geometrie (1935-36)," "Reelle Funktionen (1936-37)," "Farbenlehre (1936-37)," "Differentialgeometrie (1936-37)," "Reasons for teach. econ. (undated)"
    - Diaries, 1917-1922 (Box 33)
      One notebook dated 1917 containing collected quotes and ideas. A set of diaries numbered 1-3. Diary 1 begins December 15, 1918 and ends December 31, 1919. Diary 2 begins January 1, 1920 and ends December 31, 1921. Diary 3 covers parts of 1922.
    - Autobiographical Writings, 2 folders (Box 33)
      A number of undated notebooks containing various recollections of Menger's life. Some of the writing is illegible or in an unknown shorthand. Years mentioned in the recollections include 1905, 1908, 1913, 1918, 1932, and 1934.
  - Notebooks by Others, 12
    - Axamit, Hilda, 1933-1934; 2 folders (Box 34)
      Notebooks filled with Hilda Axamit's student notes from courses taught by Karl Menger and Hans Hahn from 1933-1934.
    - Hahn, Hans, 1912-1929 and undated; 1 folders (Box 34)
      A larger notebook containing several smaller notebooks written by Hans Hahn. Notebooks include: "Die Anfänge der Variationsrechnung (undated)," "Mengenfunktionen, Integration, Differentiation (taught in WS 1928/29 and SS 1929)," "Variationsrechnung (taught WS 1912/13 and SS 1913)," "Variationsrechnung (undated)," "Proseminar: [?] Spiele (undated)"
    - Schreier, Otto, undated; 1 folders (Oversize-box 1)
      Photocopy of handwritten version of Otto Schreier's article "Über die Erweiterung von Gruppen." Perhaps part of his 1923 dissertation under Prof. Furtwängler.
    - Unknown Authors, 1923; 1930; undated; 1 folders (Box 34)
      Notebooks in unidentifed hands. Titles include: "Leuses Differentialgeometrie Teil II (SS 1923)," "Differentialgeometrie (presumably Teil I, but cover is missing)," "Differential und Integral [?] II (1930) (author's first name and last initial on first page but illegible)," On the Generalized Method of Summation (undated) (appears to be an English-German translation)," "Theorem: Zu jedem metrischen Quadrupel Q gibt es höchstens zwei Kügelflächen in die dasselbe einbettbar ist (penned by J. Groiß?)
  - Research Notes, 13
    - Looseleaf research notes in German, English, and shorthand, undated; 38 folders (Box 35-39)
      In Folder 8, there are a large number of notes written on the back of printed material from 1918.
- Academia, 5
  The Academia Series includes materials from Menger's teaching and professional engagement, including lecture notes, syllabi, exams, and course handouts; work by his students; conference announcements and proceedings; and other reports and materials accumulated during his career as a professor.
  - Teaching Materials, 14
    - Problem sets, exercises, course handouts, printed materials, and teaching notes, 1937-1972 and undated; 21 folders (Box 45)
      Includes portions of Boston College Mathematical Series Co-op Unit Study Program by Stanley Bezuszka (1960-61) Course 1; Problem sets for the College Entrance Examination Board's Advanced Placement Exam in Mathematics; Part of an address to the Illinois Section of the Mathematical Association of America on teaching high school math by Karl Menger (May 10, 1958); Grant proposal to National Science Foundation for developing curriculum for Pre-Limit Calculus (1962); two short pieces by Karl Menger entitled "A New Approach to the Teaching of Intermediate Mathematics" and "Substitutive Function Algebra and the Calculus of Propositions"; test questions on half-sheets of paper sent to the Science Research Associates and the Professional Examination Service; numerous other publications and printed materials about teaching of mathematics in secondary and undergraduate education.
    - Broadside: "Die Lehrtätigkeit der Unwissenden und der Unfähigen auf einem Gebiete des deutschen Unterrichtswesens", undated (Box 45)
    - Various testing materials, including tests for the Future Engineers of America Tournament, 1959-60 and undated (Box 45)
    - Various teaching material and notes., undated (Box 45)
    - Miscellaneous notes by Menger's students, undated (Box 45)
    - Student work by Eric Bajars, 1964-68 (Box 47)
      Notes and dissertation draft written by one of Menger's students, Eric Bajars.
    - Student dissertations, 1933, 1946 (Box 47)
      Otto Schreiber (1933). Vincent J. Cushing "Mathematics of Thermodynamics" (1946).
  - Professional Service, 15
    - Various conference announcements, 1935-1984 and undated (Box 47)
    - Various conference proceedings, 1961-1978 and undated (Box 47)
    - Special Notes by K.M., provided to various institutions, 1937, 1954, 1959 and undated (Box 47)
    - Miscellaneous memos, reports, and agendas, 1937-1979 and undated (Box 47)
- Carl Menger Papers, 6
  The Carl Menger Series consists of files created and maintained by Karl Menger's father, the economist. The series includes correspondence, arranged alphabetically by correspondent, as well as writings and miscellany. Additional materials about Carl Menger can be found in the Carl Menger Papers, also held by the Rubenstein Library.
  - Böhm-Bawerk, correspondence, 1910-1913 (Box 48)
  - Conrad, Johannes, correspondence, 1900-1909 (Box 48)
  - Mataja, Viktor, correspondence, 1910-1921 (Box 48)
  - Montemartini, Giovanni, correspondence, 1909-1913 (Box 48)
  - Sax, Emil, correspondence, 1900-1916 (Box 48)
  - Schüller, Richard, correspondence, 1912-1921 (Box 48)
  - Schumpeter, Joseph, correspondence, 1911-1918 (Box 48)
  - Spann, Othmar, correspondence, 1909-1920 (Box 48)
  - Wicksell, Knut, correspondence, 1920-1921 (Box 48)
  - Wiesner, Julius, correspondence, 1912-1916 (Box 48)
  - Wolf, Julius, correspondence, 1908-1913 (Box 48)
  - Zuckerkandl, Robert, correspondence, 1900-1921 (Box 48)
  - Miscellaneous letters to Carl Menger, 1882-1920 (Box 48)
  - Writings (Box 48)
    Several pieces by Carl Menger including a copy of Emil Kauder's edition of Menger's "Grundsätze" commissioned by the University of Hitotsubashi in Tokyo that shows Menger's notes alongside the published text.
  - Miscellaneous academic documents, 1896, 1900 (Box 48)
    One document in Czech and one in Latin conferring honors on Carl Menger.
  - Clippings, 1894-1906 and undated (Box 48)
    Miscellaneous clippings related to Carl Menger.
- Personal Files, 7
  - Biographical Information, 2000 (Box 48)
    Photocopies of information requested by Berthold Schweizer regarding Karl Menger and the V-12 Program. Provided by Angie Kindig at the Archives of the University of Notre Dame.
  - Clippings, Keepsakes, 1872, 1925, and undated (Box 48)
    Miscellaneous clippings and keepsakes including student records, caricatures, and watercolor painting.
  - Copyright Materials, 1956-1966 (Box 48)
    Certificates of Registration of a Claim to Copyright
  - Financial Papers, 1934-1969; 4 folders (Box 48)
    Miscellaneous financial records.
  - Interview with Bonnie Schulman and Abe Sklar, 2006 (Box 48)
    Tapes and transcript of interview with Bonnie Schulman and Abe Sklar reminiscing on Karl Menger.
  - Photographs, undated; 1 folders (Box 48)
    A small collection of personal photographs.